{"tossups": [{"question": "This man's opinion in <em>Barron v. Baltimore</em> refused to apply Bill of Rights protections to state governments. He was the target of Andrew Jackson's derisive remark \"now let him enforce it,\" and he asserted his Court's power in a case about \"midnight appointments.\" For 10 points, name this Chief Justice whose ruling in <em>Marbury v. Madison</em> asserted the power of judicial review.", "answer": "John <b><u>Marshall</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Pope Leo I convinced Attila the Hun not to perform this kind of action. This kind of action was done by Gauls following the 390 BC Battle of the Allia. In 410 AD, Alaric led an army of Visigoths in performing this action, which St. Jerome identified as the effective end of the Empire. For 10 points, identify this action in which the \"eternal city\" is pillaged.", "answer": "<b><u>sack of Rome</u></b> (or descriptive equivalents, prompt on answers not mentioning Rome)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "The formation of this institution triggered the Key West Agreement on its proper usage, which was negotiated on its behalf by its first secretary, Stuart Symington. This organization conducted Project Blue Book, a study of UFOs, and it operates Area 51. For 10 points, name this branch of the US military which operates B-52s, F-16s, and other fighter jets.", "answer": "United States <b><u>Air Force</u></b> [or <b><u>USAF</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In 1970, the concluding game of this event featured the dramatic entrance of an injured Willis Reed. This event included the \"flu game\" in 1997 and an upset in 2011 that put a championship in the hands of Jason Terry, Shawn Marion, and Dirk Nowitski. For 10 points, name this annual June event, which awards the Larry O'Brien trophy to teams such as the Bulls, Heat, or Lakers.", "answer": "the <b><u>NBA Finals</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This country's banks, which had been largely taken over by Russian organized criminals by 2013, underwent a savings account \"haircut.\" This country\u2019s \"enosis\" (<b>pr. ee-NOH-siss</b>) movement propelled Archbishop Makarios to power, sparking an invasion that still divides this island. For 10 points, name this country with Greek and Turkish sectors on an island.", "answer": "<b><u>Cyprus</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This instrument was invented by a Belgian seeking a solution to the problem of clarinets raising their pitch when overblown. This instrument was played by Cannonball Adderley as well as the composer of <em>Giant Steps,</em> John Coltrane. For 10 points, name this classical and jazz instrument which has alto and tenor varieties and is a woodwind made out of brass.", "answer": "<b><u>sax</u></b>ophone [or alto <b><u>sax</u></b>ophone or any other particular kind of saxophone]", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "In 1985, this company sued Minolta over the distinctive crossed letters in its logo. This company is the descendent of Standard Oil of New Jersey, and it employed Joseph Hazelwood, who was accused of being responsible for a 1989 disaster on Prince William Sound. For 10 points, name this company whose <em>Valdez</em> tanker caused a huge oil spill, eleven years before it merged with Mobil.", "answer": "<b><u>Exxon</u></b> Mobil Corporation", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The first Church council named for this place endorsed ultramontanism and espoused the doctrine of Papal infallibility. The second council named for this place introduced the vernacular mass and renounced anti-Semitism. For 10 points, identify this namesake of 1868 and 1962 Catholic ecumenical councils, which is also the independent state where the Pope lives.", "answer": "<b><u>Vatican</u></b> City", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man refused to continue working on the film <em>The Golden Age</em> after denouncing his collaborator, Luis Bu\u00f1uel, for \"communism and atheism,\" three years after he completed <em>Un</em> <em>Chien Andalou</em> (<b>pr. uh shee-EN on-da-LOO</b>) For 10 points, name this Spanish surrealist who painted <em>The Persistence of Memory</em>, which shows several melting watches.", "answer": "Salvador <b><u>Dal\u00ed</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Misc Arts"}, {"question": "Nobility serving under this dynasty followed the \"Table of Ranks\" to determine bureaucratic advancement. This royal house came to power after three different \"False Dmitris\" were suppressed during the Time of Troubles. For 10 points, name this house founded by Mikhail I in 1613, which remained in control of Russia until the twentieth century.", "answer": "<b><u>Romanov</u></b> Dynasty  <b>NHBB C 2014-2015 </b> <b>Bowl Round 1 </b> <b>Second Quarter </b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man's reforms were sabotaged when Qi (<b>pr. CHEE</b>) sent dancing girls and horses to distract the Duke of Lu. This man advocated the \"reification (<b>pr. RAY-iff-uh-CAY-shun</b>) of names\" and the \"five relationships.\" For 10 points, name this author of the \"Five Classics\" whose sayings, collected in the <em>Analects</em>, form the basis of a traditional Chinese ruling philosophy.", "answer": "<b><u>Confucius</u></b> [or <b><u>Kong</u></b> Qiu; or <b><u>Zhongni</u></b>; or <b><u>Kong</u></b>zi; or Master <b><u>Kong</u></b>; or <b><u>Kong</u></b> Fuzi]", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {"question": "During this century, the Ottoman Empire's Tulip Period began with the Treaty of Passarowitz (<b>pr. puh-SAH-roe-vits).</b> At the end of this century, the White Lotus Rebellion broke out in China. The Battle of Plassey and the Black Hole of Calcutta took place in this century. For 10 points, identify this century in which Britain took control of Canada after the French and Indian War.", "answer": "<b><u>18th</u></b> century AD [or <b><u>1700</u></b>s]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "Alexander Neckham first described the European use of this object, which began in 1190 after it was invented in China. This object was used in conjunction with Portolan charts to double the Venetian trading season, which previously relied on clear skies for navigation. For 10 points, name this navigational device which uses the Earth's magnetic field to point north.", "answer": "<b><u>compass</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "The Ford administration declared this phenomenon \"public enemy number one\" and circulated buttons which encouraged Americans to \"whip\" this thing \"now.\" Paul Volcker was instructed by the Reagan administration to get this thing under control at any cost to the unemployment rate. For 10 points, identify this phenomenon of generally rising prices.", "answer": "<b><u>inflation</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This state's Jackson County is where the Garden of Eden was located in Mormon belief. This state was added to the U.S. as a slave state in exchange for Maine coming in as a free state, in its namesake \"compromise.\" For 10 points, name this state that shares its name with the longest river in the USA, which meets the Mississippi River here near the Gateway Arch in St. Louis.", "answer": "<b><u>Missouri</u></b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "This man first came to prominence by suppressing the 13 Vend\u00e9miaire (<b>pr. VON-deem-yair</b>) rebellion with what Thomas Carlyle called \"a whiff of grapeshot.\" He made his brothers Joseph and Jerome into the kings of Spain and Westphalia, respectively. For 10 points, name this \"First Counsel\" who was defeated by the Duke of Wellington at Waterloo.", "answer": "<b><u>Napoleon</u></b> Bonaparte [or <b><u>Napoleon I</u></b>; prompt on <b><u>Bonaparte</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "A scandal leading up to this ballot question involved abusive Twitter messages sent to J.K. Rowling. Alistair Darling appeared in an August 2014 debate on behalf of Better Together, which led the \"no\" campaign on this question. For 10 points, identify this September 2014 ballot question which sought to make Edinburgh the capital of a new sovereign country.", "answer": "<b><u>Scottish independence</u></b> referendum [or obvious equivalents]", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "Troops who carried out this action referred to it as \u201cBlumenkrieg\u201d, a term meaning \"war of flowers,\" because they were met by cheering crowds. Kurt Schuschnigg (<b>pr. SHOOS-neg</b>) was forced to resign to clear the way for this action, which began on March 11, 1938. For 10 points, identify this forced incorporation of Austria into Nazi Germany.", "answer": "<b><u>Anschluss</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>The use of this three word phrase ended a secret program by which Ryan Crocker</u></b> <b><u>coordinated the capture of Al-Qaeda operatives. This phrase originally ended with the</u></b> <b><u>word \"hatred\" when David Frum wrote it into a section of the</u> (+) 2002State of the Union Address that argued for the overthrow of Saddam Hussein</b>. (*) For 10 points, give this three-word phrase used by George W. Bush to describe Iraq, Iran, and North Korea by analogy to an earlier grouping of Germany, Italy, and Japan.", "answer": "\"<b><u>axis of evil</u></b>\"", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A major book about these places was based heavily on the recollections of Georg Tenno.</u></b> <b><u>These places were initially described only in \"samizdat\" literature, whose (+)</u> possession could get a person sent to these places, which were the subject of the (*) </b><em>Kolyma Tales</em>. For 10 points, name these places whose \"archipelago\" is the subject of a book by Alexander Solzhenitsyn, who also set <em>One Day in the Life of Ivan Denisovich</em> in one of these forced Soviet labor camps.", "answer": "<b><u>gulag</u></b>s", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "<b><u>During this era, Josquin des Prez (</u></b><u>pr. JOHS-kin day PRAY</u><b><u>) made advances in polyphony</u></b> <b><u>(puh-LIFF-uh-nee), and Giovanni da Palestrina wrote the (+)</u></b> <em><b>Pope Marcellus Mass</b></em><b>. This era's music came under fire at the Council of Trent and was succeeded by the (*) </b>Baroque period. For 10 points, identify this period in Western musical history in which motets and masses were the dominant form of music, and which shares its name with a \"rebirth\" in literature and visual arts.", "answer": "the <b><u>Renaissance</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b><u>This substance was the subject of the \"Letter to Queen Victoria\" sent by Commissioner</u></b> <b><u>Lin, who burned chests full of it on the beach. This substance was mixed with alcohol to</u></b> <b><u>make the eighteenth-century medicine (+)</u> \"laudanum\" and was consumed in namesake \"dens.\" The seizure of the </b><em><b>Arrow </b></em><b>sparked a second (*)</b> war named for this substance. For 10 points, identify this narcotic whose first war ended when the Treaty of Nanking granted European concessions in China.", "answer": "<b><u>opium</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Herbert Fairbank first explained the potential for this system in 1939 after expanding</u></b> <b><u>the Pershing Map. This system was authorized by a 1956 law but not completed until 1992,</u></b> <b><u>at a cost of 114 (+)</u> billion dollars. This system was championed by Dwight Eisenhower, who had seen the uses of the (*)</b> Autobahn system while serving in Germany. For 10 points, identify this road network which includes even-numbered east-west routes and odd-numbered north-south routes.", "answer": "<b><u>Interstate</u></b> Highway System [or <b><u>interstate highways</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Russell S. Penniman found a cheaper way to make this product, which must be</u></b> <b><u>periodically rotated to avoid the pooling of its active component out of the (+)</u> sawdust medium. This product reduced the danger of using black powder or unmodified (*) </b>nitroglycerin, and led to its inventor being dubbed \"the merchant of death.\" For 10 points, identify this explosive with mining and military applications, which requires a blasting cap and was devised by Alfred Nobel.", "answer": "<b><u>dynamite</u></b> (do not accept or prompt on TNT)", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Misc Science"}, {"question": "<b><u>Roger Ascham described the use of this weapon in the manual</u> </b><em><b><u>Toxophilus</u></b></em><b><u>, and it</u></b> <b><u>survived in the British army until World War II, when Jack Churchill killed a Nazi soldier</u></b> <b><u>with one of them. These weapons were sometimes named for the (+)</u> Welsh people who invented them and perfected their use, and they were used to great effect by the English at (*)</b> Agincourt (<b>pr. AA-jin-core</b>). For 10 points, name this six-foot-tall archery weapon which replaced the crossbow.", "answer": "<b><u>longbow</u></b> [prompt on <b><u>bow</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This city was divided by a 1946 enforcement of the Smoke Control Ordinance under</u></b> <b><u>David Lawrence. Factory workers in this city told of Joe Magerac and invented a method</u></b> <b><u>of cooking steak that produces a charred exterior and raw inside. This city was where (+)</u></b> <b>Pinkerton detectives were hired to break the Homestead strike by Henry Clay Frick and Andrew (*) </b>Carnegie. For 10 points, name this former center of steel production, which is at the head of the Ohio River in Western Pennsylvania.", "answer": "<b><u>Pittsburgh</u></b> <b>NHBB C 2014-2015 </b> <b>Bowl Round 1 </b> <b>Tiebreakers/extras \u2013 ONLY READ IF TIED OR IF A BACKUP QUESTION IS NEEDED! </b> <b><u>Because two million acres in this American state were set aside for veterans, the land</u></b> <b><u>became known as the \"Military Tract\" and towns there were named Pompey, Solon, and</u></b> <b><u>Scipio. This state's \"burned-over district\" was the center of the (+)</u> Second Great Awakening, and its city of (*)</b> Cooperstown became the home of the Baseball Hall of Fame due to an erroneous belief that the game was invented there. For 10 points, name this home of the Finger Lakes and Buffalo.  ANSWER: <b><u>New York</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}